Professional Resume Education

Frank Berardelli, Jr. 103 South Waterford Road Dalton, Pa 18414 570-815-6185 fjberardelli@gmail.com

Summary

I have 10 years of teaching experience in Pennsylvania. I am a middle school teacher in the Abington Heights School District located in Clarks Summit, PA where I teach 8th grade science. I teach under an Instructional II General Science grades 7-12 Pennsylvania certification.

Experience

Abington Heights School District

Aug. 2015 - present

Middle School Science Teacher

- Currently teach 8th grade sciences.
- Curriculum focuses on teaching the scientific method, the tools of science, cellular biology, heredity, and intro to chemistry, which includes how to interpret the periodic table, balance equations, understand chemical bonding.
- My personal 2016 PVAAS growth index score was a 2.92 (DARK BLUE) based on the PSSA Science, Grade 8, Abington Heights Middle School students' scores. Students under my direction exceeded the standards for PA Academic Growth.
- Member of the Middle School Faculty Safety Committee (2015- present)
 - This committee meets throughout the school year to work with administration on our school safety efforts. Items we are involved in include intruder safety protocol, fire and extreme weather safety protocol, evacuation procedure protocol. Working to sure up our responses as a school to such these events by developing a communication and response strategy school wide. We also work on general safety issues, which occur on a daily basis school-wide.

Old Forge School District

Aug. 2008 – Aug. 2015

Secondary Science Teacher

- Taught grades 7-9 Sciences.
- Courses taught include; Life Science, Current Events in Science, Earth/Space Science, Environmental Science, Physical Science
- 2008-2011 I taught Honors Physical Science.
- My personal 2014 PVAAS score was a 3.15 (DARK BLUE) based on the PSSA Science, Grade 8, Old Forge SD students' scores. Students under my direction exceeded the standards for PA Academic Growth.
- Math & Science Club co-advisor (Sept. 2012 2015).
 - Co-coordinated all aspects of this club including fundraising, maintenance of club bylaws and rules, locating and investigating competition events for the club members, training and preparation of club members for competitions, conducting meetings, training club officers. The club grew to a total of 80 active members during my involvement. Competitions included: Pennsylvania Junior Academy of Science, Bloomsburg Math, Science Olympiad, Moody's Math Challenge, NEIU19 STEM K'NEX challenge, Bloomsburg Iditarod.
- Member of the High School Faculty Discipline Committee (Aug. 2008 2015)
 - This committee worked with administration to promote school wide positive behavior effort. We developed and planned the annual events based on data provided by the administration and input form administrators, teachers, and students.
 - I personally designed and implemented the Fall & Spring, School Wide Positive Behavior Fun Days program and activities. Students were rewarded for displaying positive behavior throughout the school year on these

days by conducting activities including a barbeque, games, and grade level competitions. This was a school wide event including grades 7 through 12.

- Member of the High School Truancy Committee (Sept. 2011 2015)
- NEIU 19 Stem program advisor (Aug. 2008 2015)
- Provided homebound instruction for OFSD students
- Assistant Varsity Football Coach (2012 present)

Lakeland Junior / Senior High School

Secondary Science Teacher

• Taught grade 7 Life Science and Current Issues in Science to a mixed classroom of grades 10 - 12.

Relevant Secondary Experience

- I have 22 years of high school varsity and college football coaching experience. During my 5 year football coaching tenure at Old Forge our teams have compiled a 55-12 win loss record. We won three consecutive district II championships, we have reached the Pennsylvania State playoffs three times, compiling a playoff record of 9-3, appearing the Pennsylvania Class A Eastern Final twice, Pennsylvania Class A Eastern State Championship, and we appeared in the 2013 Pennsylvania State Championship game in Hershey, PA which we lost in overtime.
- I have personally coached eight Pennsylvania 1st team all-state football players including four players I was
 individually responsible for their positional development. Three of the four received scholarships to play football
 in college. I have also coached at Kings College, North Pocono SD, Tunkhannock Area SD, Abington Heights
 SD, Scranton SD, Scranton Preparatory School. Positions held have included Head Coach, Defensive
 Coordinator, and Offensive Coordinator.
- I coach Track & Field throws at Scranton Preparatory school and have had three state qualifiers and two state medalists during my tenure.
- Worked at Keystone Job Corp Center in Drums, PA as a recreation advisor 2007-2008. I designed and
 implemented recreation programs designed specifically to provide the students employability skills and
 provide them with education reinforcement. I also implemented and conducted a Math & Science
 activity program for the students at the center.

Education & Credentials

East Stroudsburg University, East Stroudsburg, PA

Master of Science / Concentration in Biology

GPA: 3.32

The University of Delaware, Newark, DE

B.A. English GPA: 2.2

Graduated 2007

December. 07 – June 08

Graduated 1992

Accreditations

Pennsylvania Level II, Professional Educator Certification

Additional Highlights and Skills

- Member PSEA Pennsylvania State Education Association
- Past Member PSFCA Pennsylvania Scholastic Football Coaches Association
- Township Supervisor (Elected) Glenburn Township, Glenburn, PA 2007-2010
- Appointed member of the Glenburn Township Zoning Board 2010 present
- Currently own and operate two successful businesses with a business partner. Both businesses are in their 16th year of operation.

 Age 51. Married since 1989 to Lisa F. Berardelli. Son Dylan is 23 is a football coach at Western New England University and graduate of Hamilton College in Clinton NY. Daughter Sierra is 21 and is a junior attending Kutztown University.

References Included with Portfolio